Each viral social media meme explosion
is like a 2 and 1/2 day panic cycle.
[music] It was not that long ago grown
men in serious positions of power and
authority in the US got mad at each
other and would literally have a
physical duel and that was like a normal
part of life. If you're sitting at home
scrolling social media getting mad, at
least you're not out in the street like
hurting people. The fact that political
violence is at like an all-time low in
Western society is something that people
[music] really don't talk about. The
news is called the news, not the
importance. If you can imagine a version
of the news that's called the importance
[music] and and the newspaper is like
here are all the important things that
are happening today. Nobody would buy it
cuz nobody cares. Cuz people want the
news. They want the hot thing. They want
the outrageous thing.
Mark, thank you for joining Monitoring
the Situation.
Good morning. I could not be more
excited. Let's monitor some situation.
Excellent. Well, first we'll we'll get a
bit meta here and uh we'll talk about
media. We've been uh talking about this
idea at Monitoring the Situation. We've
talked about investing in it for almost
a year now. Um and when we were first
talking about the idea, uh you had
brought up the the book about the
history of CNN. And you actually uh you
talked about this concept that they had
called Randomonium. Uh
what did you find so interesting about
the the founding or the history of of
CNN and how how it could apply to what
we're doing here or or this broader
media moment?
Yeah, so uh so one is I'm old enough to
remember when CNN started. Um although I
didn't actually have cable TV at the
time so I didn't see it, but uh I
remember it and the impact that it had
and then I because I'm an obsessive, I
there's this book at one point that
nobody's read, but it's the book is
called Me and Ted Against the World.
Uh which is a great title. So it's it's
uh the founder of CNN, this guy Reese
Reese Schonfeld.
Um and uh he he basically he's actually
the guy who who convinced Ted Turner to
go into the go into the satellite
business which sort of created, you
know, my essentially modern, you know,
cable TV uh satellite TV and then all
you know, led downstream to streaming
and everything else going on today. And
so
and you know, this has been kind of lost
to history, but Ted Turner was like a a
great like amazing example of like
exactly the kind of, you know, great
founder that we work with. Like just
this like incredible world of power, you
know, very controversial character. Like
every other thing out of his mouth like
horrified, like you you know, he
generated a huge number of headlines of
like you know, I can't believe Ted said
that.
Um like over and over and over again. So
like one one of these one of the one of
these real characters in the in the
history of the media business. Uh and
then this guy Reese Schonfeld who was
originally the lawyer that that wired up
Ted's first first first first satellite
deal and and so the the two of them came
up with this crazy idea like I forget
like 1981 or something. And they said,
"How about having a 24-hour news
channel?" Right? And and and this at the
time was like just like a completely
loopy idea. Uh actually uh Ted Ted
Turner wanted to be a 15-hour a day news
channel cuz he assumed that there would
be nobody watching overnight, you know,
that the 9 hours overnight. And Reese
was like, "Nope, 24 hours. People are
going to stay up all night to watch this
thing."
Um and the idea was uh by the way
completely alien to what
CNN is today.
Uh the the idea was was was this concept
that Reese Schonfeld came up with called
Randomonium which basically says at any
point in time there is like whatever
there there is something happening in
the world that is like the most amazing,
interesting, controversial, bonkers,
compelling, transfixing thing that you
can imagine.
Um and you know
>> The current thing.
>> The current thing. The current thing.
Exactly. The current thing. At any
moment in time there's the current
thing. And so he's like, "What should a
24-hour news channel be? Obviously, it
should be the thing it's right
Obviously, what it should do is it
should lock onto the current thing. It
should then cover the current thing
continuously, right? For as many
minutes, hours, or days as that thing is
the current thing."
Uh and then he called it Randomonium cuz
he basically said for that period you
just put whatever you get you put on
screen.
Um and so you get whatever fragmentary
reports or man-on-the-street interviews
or like you know, what what whatever it
is, you just like slap the thing on the
screen and like if you know, if you get
it wrong, you apologize later, but like
you know, we're you know, this is you're
real time, it's live. Um and then you
just people are just going to be glued
to this thing. And actually that So
okay, so that was the original CNN
business plan.
They they then they then you know, they
took a while to get up and running, but
then they they actually did implement
this and the the for for our older
viewers will will remember as I do that
it was the real breakthrough point was
the 1991 Gulf War.
The first invasion of Iraq and the and
that was the thing that really caused
the whole thing to punch through and
there was like a week there. Where
basically just like you were just people
were just glued to CNN around the clock
cuz they had you know it was like
literally live on the ground coverage of
like you know they were in Baghdad you
know with like bombing raids happening
all kinds of crazy stuff and the Iraqi
government like just the whole thing. It
was so it was just like the most
incredible show in the world and then
quite honestly they spent the next you
know whatever 20 years you know
basically trying to trying to you know
repeat that experience and they they
repeated it every now and then with like
the Monica Lewinsky thing was that for a
while and the OJ OJ trial was that for a
little bit but. It was just kind of hard
to come up with with with the next thing
like that and then and then you know
over the last 20 years you know CNN has
kind of become something you know
completely different today let's say.
That's not that at all and then
basically what's happened is the
internet reinvented randomonium. And so
right the experience of monitoring the
situation on especially you know on on
social media and especially of course on
X.
Right specifically right
and then by the way also streaming right
the you know the other the other part of
it is streaming and now there's
obviously streaming on X but also you
know streaming on other platforms you
know YouTube and Twitch and so forth and
so the internet reinvented this and
right so
randomonium turned into you know the
current thing and then monitoring the
situation you know legitimately
justifiably became a a giant meme and so
it is time yes it is clearly time to
monitor the situation.
Why do we think the amount of current
things or randomonium or situations just
is continuously accelerating
it it seems like it's you know just the
the amount
your velocity of these moments just
keeps on increasing how do we make sense
of that?
Yeah so I think there's really two two
things that have happened that are
really different and even you know
different than the days of cable TV and
24 hour news
so one is just like the internet for
better or for worse like the internet
plugs you into the world, right? Like
the internet plugs you in.
>> McLuhan.
>> yes.
Uh Marshall McLuhan, okay, so let's cite
Marshall McLuhan actually for both of
these. So Marshall McLuhan, who was the
great media media theorist of the 20th
century, yeah, he had two key concepts
so that are relevant here. So one is the
global village. And so he had this
concept of the global village and the
concept of the global village, by the
way, he did not view as a positive.
Like he was not endorsing he was just in
his mind he was making an observation of
what was happening, which is basically
basically what he meant by that is you
you need to conceive of what he meant by
village to start with. So so village
basically means a community with a small
enough number of people where everybody
knows everybody else. So like think
about a small town or you know, a a
literal small village and everybody
knows everybody else and as a
consequence of that there's no privacy.
Right. And and and basically everybody's
up in each other's business all the
time. Um and I and and I grew up in a
small enough town, uh you know, in a
rural town where I you know, I I
experienced this. I I saw what it was
like and it was like that. Everybody
knows everybody else. By the way, it's
the same people year after year after
year. You like get to know them like way
too well. Everybody's completely up in
each up in each other's business. Like
there's basically no privacy. Um and so
you know, and by the way, one of the
reasons people leave small towns to go
to the big city is cuz they want to get
you know, they want to get away from
that. They want to they want to get to a
level of anonymity and and and have a
lot more, you know, people running
around. But but the village kind of has
that specific thing. And what he said
was basically modern media is going to
turn the entire world into a village. Um
and so you're just going to be connected
and this is, you know, pre-internet when
he said this, right?
Um but you know, it's really happened
with the internet where it's just like,
okay, you're connected to everybody all
the time. Um and and and and by the way,
like by default, um you know, he would
find this to be like a a very
entertaining thing that this is actually
happening cuz he he would say, of course
you're getting all the downstream
effects that you're getting, which is
by default it's it's it's going to melt
your brain, right? Like the
the human animal was not evolved the
human animal was evolved to have like,
you know, there's a Dunbar's number. You
can basically have a direct relationship
with like 150 people. It's sort of
famously called the Dunbar number in
sociology. Um but the global village
expects you to have a Dunbar number of
like eight billion people, right? Like
Like cuz cuz they're all right there and
they're all up in your grill, right? And
they're all telling you what they think
of you and they're all like cursing at
you and calling you names. Like and so
it's just like this like really really
brain melting experience. Um so so that
that's part one. Um so we just we
experience reality differently uh as a
result of that. And so the the the
thought experiment I I always have is,
you know, we we talk a lot about the
impact of the internet social media on
politics. It's like uh well, okay, like
imagine having social media during World
War II.
Right? Like we would have had a
completely different national uh
experience. Um you know, had like Pearl
Harbor happened with like Twitter?
Like it like
it would have been a completely
different experience than the way people
lived through, you know, Pearl Harbor in
in in in in actually 1941 with, you
know, with primarily with TV and radio.
And so anyway, so there there's a global
village thing. And then there's this
other thing that he said, which he
originally said about television.
He made this key observation. He said
this is part of his thing where he said
the medium is the message. So the the
actual medium of the of the media
technology actually determines a lot of
the message of what's received. Uh a lot
of the content. And and and specifically
he said this thing. He said, "If it's on
television, it's a television show."
Um and what he meant by that is if
something's going to be on television,
it's going to end up being turned into
the equivalent of like a half-hour
comedy or an hour-long drama. Right?
Basically, you know, the two native
media forms of of television are the
half-hour comedy or the hour-long drama.
Um and so you're you're going to get
this basically very emotion You're going
to get this very polished and sort of
glossy and produced thing that's going
to it's going to be a story and it's
going to run the way that a television
story runs or a television show runs.
Um and it's going to and and like and
every television show is like a it's a
every television show is like a morality
play, right? Every television show
basically tells a moral story of
basically people behaving badly and then
and then learning the error of their
ways and then, you know, then famously
you have like, you know, the happy
ending, right? Uh where everybody you
know, kisses and hugs.
Um and remember Seinfeld was like a huge
variation of that because remember the
the motto of Seinfeld, Larry David's
motto for Seinfeld was no learning, no
hugging.
Um and it was it was what made Seinfeld
so unique cuz every other television
show up until Seinfeld always ended with
everybody learning and hugging, right?
You learn the moral lesson and then you
you you sort of reconcile with with the
people close to you. And so every every
real life experience would get wedged
into the format of a television show and
would be turned into like this basically
this basically
this morality play.
Okay, so the internet version I I
believe the internet version of if it's
on television, it's a television show.
The internet version is if it's on the
internet, it's a viral social media
meme.
Uh right. If if if it's on the internet,
it doesn't matter what it is. By the
way, if an alien invasion happens later
this afternoon,
it will be turned into a social media
meme. Like like like and it will go
viral. And that and that's what will
happen. Right? And it will be turned
into a viral meme and it will spread
virally across the thing and then and
then, you know, human beings what they
are, that will turn into a moral panic.
You know, that that'll turn into a
full-fledged like outright, you know,
outrage and how dare you and people will
line up on each side and you sort of
tribes will form and then people will go
to war with each other on social media
and you'll have all these, you know,
basically back and forth. You know, all
all of this all of this, you know, all
all both all the humor and all the rage
of of kind of how how how meme culture
works.
And so so everything on the internet
basically whatever happens in the real
world becomes like a social media
basically social media viral moment um
meme uh complex and then, you know,
basically moral panic. Um and you know,
search for scapegoats. Um right? Like a
moral emergency. And and and and that
happens to every single new that
happens. Right? And so and then you
combine these two and it's like, okay,
for better or for worse, we're all in
the same room now. We're like literally
in the same global village and we're
sort of surfing controversial internet
meme moments over and over and over and
over again.
And as far as I can tell, like if you
look at the numbers, basically what
happens is each viral social media meme
explosion, it basically is this huge
spike up and then it's like this
half-life decay and it lasts about 2 and
1/2 days.
Uh right. And so each social media
basically experience is like a 2 and 1/2
day basically panic cycle. Um and and
then what happens is the old one isn't
necessarily ever like resolved or
reconciled, but what happens is a new
one appears, a new current thing
appears, right? And and just takes over
the the the you know, takes over the
outrage, right? And all the emotional
energy that applied to the old one apply
applies to the new one. Everybody
forgets the old one even happened. Like
a week later, you can't even remember
like
What was the social media like craze of
like 7 days ago?
I mean, it might as well have been like
a thousand years ago. Like lost to the
mists of time. Nobody knows like 7 days
ago whatever it was was the most
important thing that's ever happened.
And 7 days later, it's like it never it
never not not even a peep. Like nothing
is it's like completely gone.
Um, and so you just you're just going to
have this like basically repeated sort
of you know, emotional shotgun blast
over and over every 2 and 1/2 days, you
know, essentially forever. By the way,
this is like this is why one of my
theories is like it's not possible to
predict the outcome of politics. So like
it's everybody thinks they know what's
going to happen in the midterm elections
in November. And I'm like, okay, it's
now whatever. It's it's it's April 20th.
It's April 20th that
the election is whatever, November 6th
or whatever. All right, how many 2 and
1/2 day cycles are there between April
20th and November 6th? And I you know,
the the math majors you know, be able to
calculate that in their head, but it's I
don't know 100 or something, right? Or
120 or something like that.
Like whatever is the thing that we think
is the thing that's going to tilt the
election today,
it's going to be a hundred social media
meme cycles old. Like nobody's going to
remember anything that's happening right
now. The election is going to turn
basically on like whatever's happening
in the economy and then it's going to be
whatever is like the viral meme panic
that's happening like that day.
And so and and you could say like is
this good or bad? I don't know. Is this
better or worse than television? I don't
know. By the way, is this better or
worse than the days of radio or the days
of you know, I don't know the Pritchard
you know, the
the revolution that followed the you
know, the the arrival of of good the
printing press? Is this better or worse
than the days in which you know, we were
all reciting epic poetry around the
campfire as our former media? I don't
know. You could have like a big value
discussion about you know, which is
better or worse.
Um, I I have an argument I will make
that this notwithstanding all the
craziness this is better. But like this
is the nature of the world we live in um
and it it let put it this way.
This is we're now on autopilot. Like the
the the the shape of the media
determines the behavior basically from
here on out and and until there's
something that fundamentally displaces
uh social media like this is the world
we live in. Hence the need to monitor
the situation.
>> Amen. Is the reason why you think it's
better is because even though there's
more noise, there's more signal and as
kind of a collective global brain we get
closer to the truth or
So I I would say this um we get so a
couple things. Yeah, so one is look I
would say there
you could say this there are more truth
and more lies. Right? I so so so I would
say that it's it's both of the following
statements are true which is there's
more truth in social media than we had
in previous forms of media and they're
probably probably I mean old media had a
lot of lies by the way. So it's it's
hard to say there are more lies. But
let's just say there are plenty of lies
in social media. Like there are plenty
you know plenty of ops and in in fact
one of one of the one of the native
forms of entertainment of social media
is trying to spot the ops.
Um by the way maybe I should pitch you a
show for on MTS which is you know maybe
every day we should do an hour on let's
spot the ops right? Like what you know
which ones are real and organic which
ones you know which ones are staged
You know was somebody getting
paid behind the scenes. Um and so you
know and everybody of course focuses on
the downside and so they focus on the
fact that there's all this all the all
the all these ops and which is
certainly true. But there's also just
like the ability for somebody to tell
the truth is like much more direct and
clear uh than it was before right?
Because of because of the you know the
the collapse of the gatekeepers. And so
I I I think both of those are true. So I
think that's true and then but the the
slightly different argument that I would
make um
is that uh previous forms of media were
really good at generating physical
violence.
Um and so um the the I mean there's many
many examples of this in history but the
Spanish the Spanish Civil War um which
was kind of the the the war that kind of
pre forecasted everything that was going
to all this sort of tragedy of the of
the 20th century that followed um you
know the Spanish Civil War was kind of
basically the test bed for both
communism and Nazism uh, in the modern
world. Um, and um, uh, and uh, you know,
it it's native media format was posters.
Um, and so you literally it was like the
idea the the ability to cut printed
color propaganda posters was like the
new media technology at that time like
you right before radio.
Um, and the Spanish Civil War was like
super violent. Um, and then radio was
the technology that led to um, you know,
radio was was was the Nazi regime's
native media format. Radio was the way
that basically the the fascist regimes
got established.
Um, uh, as well as by the way as well as
FDR uh, you know, was was was primarily
a radio phenomenon. Um, you know, kind
of the rise of modern, you know, kind of
you know, it's kind of modern modern
liberalism.
Um, and then, you know, television, you
know, was the native media medium of
like you just, you know, television kind
of kicked in starting around World War
II. So it played a role, but it it then,
you know, television had a huge role to
play in in the Vietnam War.
Um, and then in all of the violent riots
of the '60s and '70s, you know, which
were kind of you know, super crazy both,
you know, across the US and Europe. Um,
and so you know, tell television has a
long history of
of leading leading to downstream
violence. Um,
you know, the fact that we haven't
actually had like the the the fact that
like political violence is at like an
all-time low in Western society is
something that people really don't talk
about. Um, and it feels like we must be
in this like super politically violent
world because everybody's so angry about
politics all the time, but like measured
political violence is is at like an
all-time low. And so so my theory is the
the ability to directly participate in
online virtual combat uh, is shunting
away a lot of the energy that in the
past would have would have translated to
street violence.
And so and so I so it's it's sort of
this thing is if if the virtual world
can become arbitrarily rhetorically
violent
without people actually getting
physically hurt. And that gives people a
way to exercise all of their anger and
rage over politics and to be able to
attack, you know, the the hated enemy
uh, without having it actually be
something that translates to physical
violence.
Um, and so so yeah, my it's like I don't
know, social media wars up, you know,
physical violence down.
Nobody wants to hear that cuz
everybody's so mad all the time about
what's happening online, but but I think
that that's character Like, if you're
sitting at home scrolling social media
getting mad, like at least you're not
out on the street like hurting people.
So, that's my That's my moral defense of
the whole thing. Well, it's fascinating
because there's kind of a different kind
of
ideological sorting happening cuz cuz
people you you say things like, "Hey,
you know, now they can't even talk to
their own families cuz they've sort of
found their tribe online that it that
agrees with them." Uh and uh you know,
it's it's no longer the people they
it's it's no longer their families and
and back in the day, you know, you
didn't have as as much uh po- po- this
or the the logic goes, as much political
polarization of the idea that I can't
even talk to someone not not from the
same side. Pa- Part of that perhaps is
because the internet allows them to find
their tribe so, you know, so strongly
and so clearly that they're able to uh
you know, have an exclusionary tribe as
well. But, I guess
one response to political polarization
argument uh is that, "Hey, at least it's
not going to uh you know, leading to
physical combat." Uh
wh- what might you say more broadly? Is
is it just overstated in general because
people also have this idea of filter
bubbles, too. But, uh of course, it in
some ways it's the opposite in the sense
that the internet exposes you to ideas
that you wouldn't have seen otherwise.
Right. Yeah, so I think people just have
a really rose-colored glasses view of
the past. The The past gets sanded off
like in part cuz we only interpret the
pa- you know, a number one is we we
weren't there. And then the modern
interpreters of the past, you know, are
often quite honestly not telling us the
truth about what happened because they
they have their own modern kind of, you
know, gloss or spin they want to put on
it.
Um and so uh but just the edges of the
past gets sanded off in in in
retrospect. But, it's just like it's
really significant like if you just
Like the easiest thing to do easiest
thing is just go go on YouTube and watch
old episodes of a TV show called All All
in the Family.
Um which was a which was a a very uh a
very famous uh successful TV show when I
was a kid. Um and All in the Family was
a microcosm uh fictional microcosm of
basically the culture wars, political
wars of the of the late '60s into the
1970s. Um and it was like, you know
there's famously this this character
Archie Bunker
who sort of represented, you know, this
is white guy and he he basically
represent great brilliant actor named
Carroll O'Connor played him and he
basically played a retrograde basically
Republican, you know, Nixon supporting
Republican in this would be in like I
don't know 1972 or something 1974.
Um who just basically was was was
painted in the show as like the most
backwards like basically archaic, you
know, knuckle dragging racist, sexist,
just like the worst possible person in
the world. And then there was his
son-in-law played by young Rob Reiner
who
Archie Bunker nicknamed Meathead. Um
which is what the character became known
as and and and Meathead was basically
just the arch progressive liberal,
right?
You know, sort of like you know, think I
don't know young Gavin Newsom or
something, right? Where he just like he
had just like the exact politically
correct approved view of the time and so
he's like, you know, super at the time,
you know, the equivalent then of super
woke, super progressive, you know, super
liberal, super enlightened on uh on all
these issues. And and the the conceit of
the show, you know, and the guy who did
create the show is this famous
television producer named Norman Lear
and the conceit of the show was supposed
to be a moral it was supposed to be a
moral lesson of Meathead giving
basically moral lectures to Archie
Bunker every week to try to get Archie
Bunker to stop being such a
backwards-looking like 1950s retrograde
basically racist sexist guy and and come
into the modern world. And of course
what happened was Carroll O'Connor
number one the actor was just like super
funny. Uh but the other was the the
political environment was superheated at
that point and and of course it turned
out Archie Bunker ended up being the
star of the show.
Uh and and so the the show ended up
being the opposite of kind of what what
it was intended to be. Uh that happened
later in the 80s it happened in the show
called Family Ties
which was again it was a very similar
thing which it was it was these two
parents baby boomer parents in the 80s
and they were like super, you know, very
left-wing producers who made the show
and the characters were like super
proper left-wing progressive. And then
there was this character in the show
Michael J. Fox their their son who was
this teenage kid, um and um he played
the I forget the name I'm I'm blanking
on the name of the character, but he
played played the son. And the son
basically was a Reagan Republican as a
teenager, right? And and literally the
son would like wear like sport jackets
and ties to school and carry a
briefcase. And they kind of wanted to
make him into like a stereotype of like
basically uh you know, sort of a weird
Republican, you know, kind of weirdo. Um
and again, the same the same sort of
weird thing happened, which is actually
the Michael J. Fox character became Oh,
uh Alex Alex Keaton was Alex uh was the
character's name. Uh Alex P. Keaton, um
you know, he essentially became the star
of the show. And so I bring up both of
those shows cuz you can see in those
shows you can see the culture wars of
the '70s, which were actually like super
intense. You can see the culture wars of
the '80s, which were super intense.
You go back before that and you have the
Vietnam War and the the all the campus
protests and the civil rights movement
and all the riots and all the forced you
know, everything, you know, dropping the
101st Airborne into you know, rural you
know, the rural South to you know,
basically, you know, desegregate the
schools at literally gunpoint. Um you go
back before that, you have the Cold War,
you know, you have the Red Scare, um you
know, it's now known as the Red Scare,
but you had, you know, communists all
through the US government and you had
all kinds of freak outs about that. You
had the risk of nuclear annihilation.
You go back before that, you had World
War II,
which was like this like just like
incredible global orgy of violence. You
go back before that, you had the Great
Depression and the you know, the New
Deal, which was hugely controversial.
You go back before that, you had World
War World War I, you know, and then you
go and then you know, if you keep going
back, it's like you have the Civil War
and then you have the Napoleonic Wars
and then you've got the French
Revolution and you know, and then you go
back further than that, you've got the
you know, the the democratic revolutions
uh all through Europe and then you've
got the you know, the the Gutenberg
printing press kicking off all kinds of
violence, you know, throughout Europe in
the 1600s. Um and so I just think like
the history of Western civilization,
American European society is just like
constant strife and warfare to like an
absurd degree um over this entire
period. And we we go back and we study
the history and we're just kind of like,
"Wow, like those people were like really
really really violent. Like really crazy
and really violent." And boy, did they
really like killing.
It was not that long ago and I don't
think there's anybody alive now, but it
was not that long ago that like grown
men like in serious positions of power
and authority in the US that they got
mad at each other, they would literally
have a physical duel.
Right? Like so you know, you and I you
and I start going at it on social media
and we get to a point where you get
really mad and I challenge you to a duel
and like we show up in a field
in a park, you know, at like
6:00 in the morning with guns, right?
And we like square off and march off and
then we turn around and we try to like
literally shoot each other to death.
And like a thing that they did and that
was like a normal part of life.
Wait, Mark, I thought the past was all
matriarchies and everyone just so
peaceful and Oh, everybody was so
wonderful. Everybody got along.
Everybody all Yes, until social media
everybody thought the same thing.
Yes, exactly and everybody was all Yes,
everybody was all calm and happy all the
time.
Um and so
You look, the the the the the the way
the way the way the world is conflict I
just historically the way the world is
conflict and anyway, not to not to beat
a dead horse, but they
you know,
There was plenty of conflict in the
past. There were plenty of heated
disagreements in the future shape of
society. There were plenty of political
wars. There were plenty of violent wars.
By the way, just politics itself was
much more violent. Like if you go back
and you read about political movements
100 years ago, like they would literally
form up in the street and like
you try to kill each other.
>> Yeah. Um like it was like a common
thing.
You know, strikes I mean even the
history of the labor movement is full of
this. Like strikes became super violent.
Um and you know, management would like
literally you know, this the strikers
would try to attack their plants and the
management literally would have like
machine guns and they'd be like machine
gunning their striking workers.
Crazy crazy stuff. And so like
we just we live in a much crazier world
than we want to give ourselves credit
for and the idea that like the current
level of conflict is something new is
just not true. And and just to that end
too, when people say, "Oh, ever since
2008 or you know, your smartphone sort
of you know, propagating that
it's led to increased depression or
things like that." Is that also another
example of hey, we were underestimating
how depressed people were prior and it's
It's of a measurement thing or is it oh,
but there was a lot of other things
happening in 2018 like you know,
political extremism and and other things
that that make people more depressed or
how do you how do you engage in that
that topic? Well, so the funny thing is
different Western countries have
different that show different data on
the quote and quote rise in in
depression. Yeah. Um and it basically
basically turns out it correlates to
social benefits programs.
Um and so basically if you get paid uh
or if you get like special dispensation
in school for having you know,
psychological issues all of a sudden you
see a massive spike in those
psychological issues. The countries that
don't have that the other Western
countries that don't have that don't
show the same results. And so I I
actually think that's a statistical
artifact uh of literally like government
benefits programs.
Um so I I like I I don't even yeah, I
would I would say I don't I don't I
don't even I don't even I don't even
concede the uh you know, concede the
premise of the question but that's
that's that's a longer debate. Um I
would just say in general like I guess
what I'd say I'm I'm I'm prepared to say
that basically call it since I don't
know, 2014 or something I'm prepared to
say like it does feel like things have
intensified. Right, it it it does feel
like things are like wilder.
Um you know, than they were before that.
Um
I think the most that I would be willing
to say though is I think we might have
lived through an era of what you might
call suppressed volatility. Um and call
that maybe from like the end of the Cold
War through 2014.
Um where basically it just looked like
the West had won everything. Um and then
also it was sort of by the way, it was
sort of the peak heyday of centralized
media. Um so it would if you just like
if you basically track if you track like
how distributed is media versus how
centralized is media like centralized
media sort of peaked somewhere around
1970.
Um where you know, literally like all
the newspapers in every city
consolidated down to like a single
newspaper and then you ended up with
only three television networks and all
the radio stations independent radio
stations got bought up.
Uh let me give you an example. So
historically so historically like if you
go back to the days of the American
Revolution it was common in in even like
mid-size cities you would have like 10
or 15 different newspapers.
Um and each newspaper would represent
like a different political point of
view. And then the the newspapers would
have these like furious you know,
they've just like just like you you
would do today online. You You They
would just have these furious constant
political, you know, fighting and
accusations back and forth and
arguments. And of course the newspaper
owners would be trying to egg all that
stuff on cuz it sold papers. But it was
like very common to have like many
newspapers per city that would all fight
with each other. And then the economics
of centralized media meant that those
all rolled up into into a single
newspaper.
Um and and then and then that single
newspaper, you know, at least for a
while tried to be non-partisan and tried
to be even-handed cuz it was trying to
appeal to everybody.
Um and then and so and again same thing
of just like, you know, like when I was
a kid there was three television
networks that were all basically the
same. Uh they were all trying very hard
to be even-handed at least, you know,
kind of as best they could.
Uh there were like three national news
magazines. Um you know, there were like
I don't know there was a small number of
national radio networks. Um you know,
there were two, you know, news wire
services. And so I like I I I will
concede like I think we lived through a
period of suppressed volatility as a
consequence of the fact that we had
overly centralized media. I think if you
go back before that, like if you go back
to before that, if you go back to like
the 1930s and before, like media was
much more fragmented. Uh it was it was
much more like it is today. And then if
you like I said, if you go all the way
back like 200 250 years ago, it was like
extremely fragmented. Like if you read
the accounts of like Ben Franklin as a
newspaper publisher and like the the the
stuff that he got up to with his
newspaper. So Okay, great story. So Ben
Franklin ran one of the newspapers in
Philadelphia originally as a as a
printer. Okay, so what would happen is
Ben Franklin wants to become a pretty
much become a commercial printer. He
buys a printing press. He advertises the
whatever and tries to get like all the
local businesses like print pamphlets in
the printing press, but he doesn't have
enough business for the printing press.
And so he starts a newspaper to have
something to print.
Um and so he starts this newspaper.
There's like 15 other newspapers in
Philadelphia at the time. But he's got
to fill the newspaper with something.
And so in he's Ben Franklin, he's very
creative. And so he creates basically
sock puppets.
He does basically He does basically
alts. He does alts. Alts. He does alts.
So Yeah, yeah, exactly. Alts. Um
and they're all under pseudonyms. Um and
so he does I forget the all the names
now, but he had, you know, he had all
these different he had all these
different different names for them. And
I think at one point in his own
newspaper he had like 15 different alts
uh going at it. And he he he he wrote
them all but under different names. And
they all had like very different points
of view. And then he would basically set
them off to have these like raging
arguments with each other in his
newspaper. And people would buy his
people would buy his newspaper to cover
this. And then that that culminated in
the election of 1800, which was the
famous election of Thomas Jefferson
versus John Adams, which was sort of
this newspaper centric election, which
was characterized by a level of slander.
Like the degree to which partisans of
Thomas Jefferson and John Adams attacked
each other in the 1800 election is like
way beyond even what we see today on
social media. Like they accused each
other of the most horrible you can
possibly imagine.
Um and it became like this giant
scandal.
And so like this is not the the idea
that there's like whatever rhetorical
combat or like that there's like this
virtual environment in which there's
lots of points of view and there's lots
of, you know, again both lots of truth
truths lots of lies. Like this is not
new. In fact, this this this is the
natural order of things.
We just lived through a period of
artificial volatility and that
artificial suppression of volatility.
Uh with media becoming over centralized.
And and and obviously those days are
over.
I want to return back to
uh we were talking about the current
thing and how that's accelerated over
time. We previously had a conversation a
while ago where we talking about sort of
the attributes of of a current thing.
And I remember you had this one theory
that it can't be something too
believable. It has to be almost surreal.
Uh
yeah. Um I'm I'm curious if we just talk
kind of what are the attributes of
something that becomes sort of the the
current thing or sort of the the the
topic that people can't stop quote
tweeting, sharing, etc.
Yeah, so
again, it's kind of this thing you kind
of reverse engineer it. It's like, okay,
to be a current thing it it has to if
you know, again to to to be this thing
of if it's on the internet, it's a viral
internet meme kind of outrage cycle. Um
so it it has to be something that like
it has to be something that activates
outrage. Like it has to be something
that activates the emotional kind of
valence
um of you you have to get like the
emotional reaction off of it. Right. Um
and so you know, it's it's just like by
the way, this is just like also the
history of the press in general.
It's just like whatever you know, I
always say, the news is called the news,
not the importance, right? Like
you can imagine a version of the news
that's called the importance. And and
the newspaper is like here are all the
important things that are happening
today.
Right? Um and you know, of course nobody
would buy it cuz nobody cares, right?
Cuz people want the news, they want the
new what the new thing, right? They want
or you know, they want they want the hot
thing, they want the exciting thing,
they want the they want the outrageous
thing and and so the the internet
version of that is right, they want they
want the outrageous meme and so so it's
got to be something that provokes. And
you know, and there's something about
this, you know, this this is other
people made this observation but you
know, it's like
you know, kind of the ultimate male
coded version of this is professional
wrestling, right? The ultimate female
coded version of this is like Real
Housewives.
Like you know, reality TV, like you
know, I don't know and then The
Apprentice is maybe somewhere in the
middle.
You know, it's just like reality TV,
like there there has to be there has to
be sparks. Like it has to generate a
level of emotional intensity.
Driven by some level of outrage and then
and then I think it has to be the kind
of thing where you can have tribes that
form up and square off against each
other, right? So um so you know, there's
a little bit like like like West Side
Story dynamic to it or something, right?
Where it's just like, okay, you can
imagine, you know, there's there's
something that's worth arguing over.
Um where where there's a you know, where
there's a real argument to be had. Like
there you know, there's there's some
underlying thing that actually like
really matters. Maybe maybe this event
doesn't matter as much but like the
actual underlying issue matters a lot.
Um and then it's going to it's going to
activate this tribal effect where you're
going to be able to basically you're
you're going to become part of what they
call a moral tribe. The the people on
the other side will become part of a
moral tribe and then you're going to
kind of go to war with each other.
You're you're going to have a rumble,
what they would have said in the old
days. You're going to have a rumble. A
rumble in the streets, except you're not
going to have a rumble in the streets,
you're going to have a rumble online,
right? You're going to go at it. And so
it has to lend itself to that kind of
basically tribal formation um and and
and and and and kind of that beating
back and forth. And of course you you
the tribes then attack each other, you
know, on the issues but then they also
attack each other's values um and they
accuse each other of being horrible
people. And then when it gets really
into it, they start to dox each other
and try to get each other fired. Right?
And then it all becomes, you know, very
exciting.
Um and so so it's got to have it's got
to have the it's basically it has to
have the formation of a of a of a moral
tribe effect. It it's a the the
psychological lens on this they call
moral tribes and then there's this
concept right of moral panic. Uh, it's
got to lead to a moral panic. It's got
to lead to this kind of thing of like
this is indicative of how society is
going to right? In in in like some
important way.
Um, and by the way, this is why you can
have like many many many many different
examples occurring things that end up
revolving back around the same handful
of like underlying political or moral
questions, right? Cuz cuz it's really
right. It's really not about the, you
know, what happened, you know, I don't
Jussie Smollett.
I I just want to say there's this new uh
there's this new um
there's this new uh Keanu Reeves movie
on on Apple TV um where uh Keanu Reeves
plays a movie star who gets canceled.
Um, and his crisis lawyer played by
Jonah Hill. Uh it turns out during the
course of the show, I'll I'll just spoil
it in course of the movie, it turns out
his his crisis lawyer
uh set up the uh the the Jussie Smollett
uh was was was off it was it was a
produced op. Um,
So so so in the movie world the lawyer
came up with the idea um that there
would be a black celebrity who would get
attacked in the street by white racists
and that would be like a viral social
media outrage thing and then and then
literally the lawyer says, "Well, then
we of course we went on cast and Jussie
Smollett had the best pitch for why he
should be he should be the black guy."
Um, and then um and then um there was
one of his underlings he he's still mad
at because the
uh the um the underling was was tasked
with the assignment of going out and
hiring, you know, the attackers. Um, but
you know, this is in the heady of
diversity and so he hired two black guys
to be the attackers.
Right? And he's like all confused cuz
he's like, "Am I supposed to hire black
people not hire black people?" And it's
like, "Well, not in this specific case
you weren't supposed to hire black
people
to attack Jussie Smollett." Anyway, so
the Jussie Smollett
is fresh in my mind. Um, but it was a
great example which is like what
happened on the street in Chicago that
night during the whatever whatever
blizzard cyclone thing it was like
kind of matters, kind of doesn't matter.
Whoever really knows, who knows
whatever. We've got weird grainy video,
whatever. People say different things. I
mean, I think we now know what happened,
but like in these events, like what
actually happened in the street? Who the
hell knows? But
the fight, you see what I'm saying? Like
the moral tribes that were able to form
up on, you know, one side or people are
like, of course this is what, you know,
this is what happens to people all the
time. And the people on the other side
of it were like, of course this is all
fake and Right? You had this
You had this chance for these moral
tribes to to to pair up and fight. Um
and so so I think I think it basically
had I think it basically it it it
basically has to have that.
Yeah, and sometimes it's very serious uh
and and the stakes are very high and
sometimes it's uh just an episode that's
so
you know,
funny and the astronomer uh CEO HR as a
as an example. Uh Okay, so well this
Okay, this is a very important point. So
very important point. So I would say two
things. So one is
um the truth or falsity
of the actual event doesn't seem to
matter at all.
And and I think this is I think this
actually throws people cuz you start to
think these are all fake and they're not
all fake. Like actual actually bad
things happen.
Right? Actually bad things happen and
it's actually like fully legitimate to
get outraged about these things. But
also people are going to get outraged
about a lot of things that actually
didn't happen. Um and so so so for the
purpose of the discussion of of the
media again, this is the Marshall
McLuhan thing. If it's on the internet,
it's a viral social media outrage cycle.
Like whatever are the facts of the
thing, it doesn't really matter. In
fact, it's probably best to your point.
It's probably best if it's actually hard
to tell what actually happened.
Cuz that makes it something that you can
more easily argue about. And so that's
one thing. And then to the point that
you just made, I really agree with that
also, which is um the the degree of
importance of the actual issue doesn't
matter that much. Right? And so if it if
so if something happens to a single
person, you can and then something
happens to 10,000 people, you can have
the same level of outrage in in each
case.
Like the the outrage doesn't scale with
the number of people affected.
Right? In a lot of In a lot of ways,
maybe the outrage is even higher when
it's a specific person cuz it's because
then it becomes personalized. Yeah. And
then and then you get in the old uh what
is it? The old Stalin thing, which is a
single death of a tragedy, a million
deaths is a statistic. Like may maybe
it's even the small scale horrible
things that happen that are the most
emotionally intense cuz they're the
things that you really you know you're
going to you're going to react to a
person. You know kind of kind of the
most intensely. And so so and I think
that's the thing if you're if you're
doing the meta observation of this it's
like okay you're just going to you
basically you just have to expect the
same phenomenon this outrage cycle to
play out every time regardless of truth
or falsehood and regardless of the
actual magnitude of the underlying issue
because
because again what's being argued about
is the specifics about what actually
happened. That's not the point. The
point is the ability to form up into
moral tribes and then and then yeah and
then have the rumble. Yeah. Oh
there's a
George Orwell um
actually has a has a great thing on this
cuz George Orwell famously covered the
Spanish Civil War which which was as I
said it's kind of the it's kind of the
original where a lot of this stuff sort
of played out for the first time in the
20th century and he he he did he did
this thing one time where he talks about
his version of this. He talks about the
role of the atrocity.
Um and he said basically the the key
point of propaganda in any war um so you
you get two countries to go to war and
you know they've each got a moral claim
of like why they're the justified you
know it's like nobody ever attacks
everybody's always defending like and I
only attacked him first cuz he was going
to attack me otherwise. And so every
each side in a war each country has its
own basically moral position why the why
the war is justified. But he said he
said basically Orwell said like it's
hard to sell like high it's hard to sell
like these high blown you know these
high high flying kind of abstract ideas
of like why we need to go to war. And so
he said what what happens is that the
propaganda efforts of each government in
a war become basically looking for
atrocities. Um
and so specific point events. A famous
one is the My Lai Massacre in in in
Vietnam. But you you could you could we
could name many many other examples. Um
and so you're looking for these very
specific events where something very
specific and concrete happened that's
clearly over the moral
beyond beyond the realm of
of moral acceptability. Right? Just
clearly like you know
usually involving innocent people
getting killed.
And in the Spanish Civil War it was like
you know nuns getting killed or
something like that, right?
Um and and and again, it's the the the
the point of the atrocity The point of
the atrocity is not that it affected
100,000 people. The point of the
atrocity is in fact, maybe the best
atrocity only affects a small number of
people cuz you want to personalize it.
Um and then he said he he he says this.
He says, "The truth or falsity of the
atrocity doesn't matter at all."
Like it it it the atrocity If the
atrocity is made up, it it it it the the
the political value of the atrocity is
just as high.
Right? And so it it doesn't matter. Like
once the atrocity cycle gets running, um
it doesn't matter whether the underlying
thing is true or false because the
because the point of it is to have the
have the atrocity be a propaganda win uh
for for moral for moral for moral
justification and then and then for
moral demonization of the other side.
And by the way, lest lest people think
that I'm being cynical when I go through
all this, I'm not saying I think this is
all good. Like I I'm not saying I think
this this world is great. I'm not saying
that this I think that this is all
positive. Um I I'm saying something
different, which is I think it's very
important to understand how this
actually works. Because when you find
yourself in the middle of one of these
things, I think it's very useful to have
at least a slice of your brain that's
basically saying, "All right, I need to
be aware of the fact that I'm getting
pulled into something, right? That I'm
being triggered by emotion and I'm being
triggered and I'm being slotted into a a
moral tribe and I'm and I'm mounting up
to go to war with the hated enemy and
it's on the basis of something that very
well might not be true." Yeah.
Right? And I and I and this, you know,
this is a the Rene Girard thing, which
he says this the scapegoating cycle
always works because people always
forget that there's a scapegoating
cycle. Like Like
whenever you have to like crucify the
scapegoat, it's always the most morally
important thing that's ever happened.
For the duration of that cycle, right?
And until it's forgotten by the next
one. Yeah. And so And so a big part of
what I'm trying to do is explain why
like as as as we surf all of these
current things, that we like at least
keep part of our brain that basically
says, "Look, th- this is the state of
the world we live in. This is the state
of humanity. This is the state of the
media. Like this is what's happening. We
can like it or hate it or we can debate
the pros and cons, but it is what's
happening, and all objective events are
going to be filtered through that. And
to the extent that you care about
objective truth, you have to get through
that, and you have to get to the other
side to be able to actually still deal
with objective reality. But But to do
that, you need to understand the the
cycle. And it's also important to
understand cuz if if people are ever
involved in the cycle or implicated in
it, they typically say, "Oh, but I'm
innocent. Once everyone finds out the
truth, they're they're going to
exonerate me. They're going to clear
me." And they of course don't fully
appreciate that people don't give a
People are, you know, predisposed to to
to hate you, and they'll just find any
sort of reason, uh, you know, or or
certain people, perhaps.
Yes. Yes. Yes. If Yes. If you are Yes.
If you are actually in a If you are
actually innocent, and if you're caught
up in one of these things, it's it's
horrifying. It's horrifying. I mean,
look at cancellation. I mean, this this
happened to a lot of people over the
last decade. You know, people people
would get canceled for things they
literally never did, and for, you know,
for for for people then imputing
beliefs, or, you know, some I don't
know, stray comment, or misreported
comment, and then it gets imputed that,
you know, this person is a horrible
racist, and off and away it goes, and
they have to get fired and purged from
society, and, you know, have no way to
come back. Or or, you know, or whatever
the issue was, right? Um, and, you know,
we you know, there were these you know,
these viral videos viral video you know,
Oh, that's the other thing is like,
okay, the the viral videos
The viral videos, right? The viral
videos have viral videos have become so
much like the By the way, the first
viral video that mattered was actually a
Rodney King. Um
And it would And it actually inaugurate
And I'm not going to I'm not going to
litigate the Rodney King good or bad or
whatever. It's a the whole separate
conversation, but
um
the Rodney King video starts with the
beating.
Um so, it doesn't show everything that
led up to that. And And And that set the
pattern. And again, I'm not I'm not
excusing anybody for anything or
whatever. I'm just saying like the video
started midway through the event. Um All
of the really effective viral videos
basically since then, including the ones
that have been really important over the
course of the last decade, they've all
had that characteristic. They all start
halfway through the event.
Um so, you you don't see the run-up. Um
and so, you don't you know, the Central
Park birdwatcher was the famous like you
don't see the run-up of what happened
before the before before the video
started.
Um what was the other one? Who was the
other person who got like brutally
canceled based on a video? I can't
remember. I mean, there've been a whole
bunch of them. But, um this is the
thing. Right. And so, you you you get a
viral video and it kicks off halfway
into the event. Why does it kick By the
way, why does it kick off halfway into
the event? That's because that's when
the event became interesting enough to
be able to put on a video.
Like that's what People don't just like
walk around with their phones out.
That's when they pull the phone out.
But, by that point, you've lost all the
context. Right? And so, so then again,
this is one of those things where, okay,
you're watching a viral video, you can
feel yourself getting outraged. The key
question ought to be, all right, what
happened before that?
Right? And you And that takes work,
right? Like cuz it's not it's not right
there on the screen. And you have to
like really try hard to like go back and
like figure out eyewitness reports. And
by the way, like if it's a criminal
thing, half the time you don't find out
what happened until the actual trial
happens. So, you don't find out for like
another year. Because they don't put the
evidence out until the trial. Um and so,
that that's another thing where people
get got basically people get used
basically people get ginned up into
these outrage cycles without actually
having the context of what happened.
Yeah.
The
I want to go back to this conspiracy you
know, we have a a friend who thinks
everything is an op and maybe I'm naive
and I miss out on on the ops that are
actually there. But, I'm I'm curious
what your mental model one might have to
think about how much is coordinated
versus not. I've I've I've been inspired
by the idea of uh
uh decentrali- or emergent collusion. Uh
just sort of um this this idea that a
lot of people have incentives to go in
the same way that even if they're not
coordinating explicitly, they almost
might as well be or something that that
or that it might explain
why so many things seem uh coordinated.
But, you know, ever since joining A16Z,
so many people have impuned onto us
things that we're not doing. And so,
it's made me skeptical of uh of people
calling for conspiracy. Um and and so,
I'm curious what what sort of mental
model you might have for for for the
idea of ops and how that might help one
understand the the the social platforms
today.
Yeah, so I think as best I can tell, and
it's tricky cuz it's hard to tell. Um
and there are, you know, some real
experts in this that really really focus
on this. But, um as far as I can tell,
like there there's some there's there
there's some truth on both sides. Um
the the the the the the answer is um is
the answer is messy. And it's it's messy
for two reasons. So, messy number one is
just like there are a lot of things that
I think are happening that are truly
organic. And then there are a lot of
things that are happening that are ops.
Um and I I think I think there's a
combination. And then and then I think
maybe you were alluding to this. And
then there's this thing which is like
something could start as an op and then
become real.
Right? Um which is kind of the point of
the op, right? The the the
Right? The If you Let's just say if you
and I are going to be Machiavellian and
we wanted to start a movement, right?
And I And we wanted to start a moral
outrage cycle cuz we had some underlying
goal cuz we were either trying to win an
election or trying to get a political
something, you know, law passed or
something like that. We were going to
like we're maximum like Machiavellian
deviousness and we're going to like have
a black budget, you know, and we're
going to pay influencers to you know, da
da da all this stuff that people say,
you know, bot we're going to have our
bot army and so forth. Like the point of
it is not to just like have a bunch of
propaganda online with a with a bot army
behind it. The point is to get people to
actually believe it.
Right? Like that is the goal.
Right? And so and and and and then you
know, you don't want to have to pay for
like every post, right? At some point
you want them to be happening
organically even just out of out of
self-economic interest. And so you you
actually you're actually trying to
generate uh you're actually trying to
generate uh the thing. Actually, there's
there's a great paper on this. Um
There's a guy Timur Kuran and and uh
who's the famous sort of a guy who talks
about preference falsification. And then
Cass Sunstein um wrote this thing years
ago or they they talk about this
phenomenon relevant here. They call it
availability cascades. So, their term
for this kind of thing that we've been
talking about, which is like a viral
outrage cycle, uh their term for it they
call availability cascade. And what they
mean by availability cascade is sort of
cascade means basically the process it's
the sociological term for sort of an an
idea or concept kind of cascading
through a society kind of building a
momentum as it goes. And then
availability they they they they call
based on the idea of availability bias,
which basically is we we to overfocus on
the thing that's right in front of us.
Um and so we we tend to over focus on
the thing that's basically present in
our mind at that time, which may or may
or may not be as important as other
things that we're not focused on. But
But in the paper the significance of it
is in the paper they identify the role
of a specific kind of person they call
availability entrepreneur.
Um and the the role of the availability
entrepreneur is to try to inject into
the public consciousness availability
bias as a deliberate exercise to
basically say, "This is the specific
thing that you should be focused on
right now."
Like this is the specific person who's
been hurt by something. This is the
specific whatever, you know, moral event
that's happened. This is the specific
issue. This is the specific thing. And
And basically what they say is like
every time you see an availability
cascade, if you trace it back there was
always what they call the availability
entrepreneur, which is basically the
person who was like, "Aha, I am going to
put I know I'll give you the classic
example. And And again, this is not a
value judgment and you know, this this
was like you know, fantastically good
that this happened. But Rosa Parks was a
classic example of this. Like Rosa Like
the story that we all got told at school
was Rosa Parks was just like another you
know, some sort of random person and you
know, with with the thing on the bus. Um
Rosa Parks was like an actual She was a
trained activist. Like that she she went
to like the There was this whole like
school of activists and they like she
was like a specifically trained It was
an It was There was an availability
entrepreneur uh uh who set up an
availability cascade targeted on Rosa
Parks that ended up causing fundamental
and obviously very very positive changes
to American society. But like
it started as an op. Like she started as
a She started as an op. But the point of
the op was not to be the op. The The
point of it was to be what happened,
which is to become a nationwide movement
that that ultimately led to led to
fundamental change. And so And so
anyway, the point is like just because
things start as ops doesn't mean they're
not real.
Right? And And And And And And And if
the And if the op leads to real
outcomes, then you might as well
consider you know, it's like a At some
point it's just a matter for historians
of how it started. Like it's a footnote
to the Rosa Parks story today that she
was a trained activist. It doesn't
really matter
because she because that op unlocked a
broad-based actual movement in American
society that led to actually profound
change. Um and so
this is the problem with this topic,
which is oh, that's just an op. Is
basically like cope. Like, okay, right?
It might have started as an op.
But if it ends up in a real thing, it
doesn't You see what I'm saying? It
doesn't matter that it started as an op.
Right. Uh and then by the way,
conversely, it also doesn't matter if it
didn't start as an
Because again, it's
it's the same outcome. And so So, I do
think I think I think both things are
true. I do think there's this furious
fight. I do think there are serious
operators. And you know,
you can go online and you can find out
about these things.
This is a big issue, by the way, in
political influencer world right now.
This is This is actually a big thing.
So, um
if I
want to run an advertising campaign to
sell shampoo,
um legally in the US, if I hire
influencers to say good things about the
shampoo, they I I believe this to be
true, they have to disclose that it's a
paid commercial.
They can't just like pretend that they
just happen to stumble on this shampoo.
Um if I donate money
to a political candidate,
I have to disclose that as part of
election federal election law.
Um if I pay an influencer to take a
position on a moral topic that is not a
product that is sold or a political
candidate,
but it's just like a position on a moral
or political thing, that doesn't qualify
either as an advertisement or as a
political donation.
It's fully legal to do that in the dark.
Yeah.
Well, right. AI, right? A lot of a lot
of paid doom out there. We were just
talking about Aella's,
you know,
>> [laughter]
>> a new media fellowship for doomers.
And yeah, it's a perfect example
and it, you know, seems to be having a
real impact.
This is a great example. So, this is the
thing, right? You know, they're they're
living the meme, right? They're living
the meme. So, cuz cuz so so this is a
good So,
so
I don't know if you you you may have
covered all this already, but yeah. So,
so like there we we know we're in this
AI we're in this pitch AI policy battle
and we we know through that and we we're
we're deep into this. We know that
there's dark money in in AI. Like, a lot
of the AI doomers and stuff is basically
bought and paid for. Like so there's
this these influence operations that are
happening and they fall into this bucket
of it it's it's it's neither an
advertisement to say AI is going to kill
everybody nor is it a political
candidate. And so you there are
organizations and companies that are
paying that you know that they're
they're they're there's that and again
it's like not not everybody who says
that is is is being paid but that there
there is a lot of dark money in in that
in in that world right now. Um and so
and of course you know that the
partisans in that world insist full on
of course that there's you know that
that of course is absolutely not
happening until yesterday. Um when they
just go ahead and like live the meme and
they just like announce the program. Um
and so
>> [laughter]
>> So they announce the program in black
and white um right there on the website.
It's like a influencer camp in which
you're going to go did that that that
that and by the way it's free right
which means you know you're you know
you're being you're being paid.
Um and then they say you know where's
the money coming from and they say oh
you know we're a non-profit being funded
by by in this case MIRI which is one one
one one organization with its own kind
of interesting funding history. And then
they say and other donors.
Right then they
Right. It's like
It's literally you know it's literally
like it's it's literally like is it you
I don't know is it a conspiracy if it's
in plain sight?
But and I'm just I'm picking on that one
cuz that's the one that happened
yesterday but like that that for sure is
happening all throughout politics. It's
for sure happening on lots and lots of
social issues.
Um you know it's it's it's a it's a
thing. Um uh and so yeah and so like but
again it goes back to this thing of like
okay yes there are ops. Yes you can't
believe what you see. By the way there
there are there are there are bot farms.
Like there are obviously bot farms. Um
and they're obviously bot farms that are
being deployed. You know there there are
online influencers some of them very
controversial where you know they
clearly there's clearly a bot army
behind them. By the way you could be an
influencer online and have a bot army
behind you and have nothing to do with a
bot army.
Right. Like somebody could be paying for
the bot army and you might not even know
about it.
Um and again today it's totally legal to
do that cuz again if it's if you're not
selling a product or not donating to a
political candidate like it's it's
actually in this gray it's actually fine
to do. And so I think it's It's
the case that like there's ops all over
the place and quite frankly, like the
longer I I you more deeper I get into
it, the more like, yeah, there's
probably more ops than I've been that
I've been um that I that I've been I've
been uh willing to acknowledge. Um but,
I would just say on the other side, it's
like
I don't know. Does it really matter?
Like
is that really the thing that the cuz
the ops are only going to work the other
way to put it is the ops are only going
to work if they if they resonate into
something that people are going to pick
up and run with
you know, anyway. Like to become a mass
movement, this is like what Timur Kuran
says about the role of the availability
like, it's not enough to just like have
your cause
and then just like expect that you can
kind of trick people into running with
your cause. There has to be something to
it that resonates with them. Uh you
know, kind of in them already. Um the
causes the causes the causes them to
Uh and and if if maybe they pick it up
and run with it based on the paid op,
and and by the way, maybe in the
counterfactual they would have picked up
and run with it anyway, you know,
without the op, and you know, you'll
never know. Yeah.
The um
that that's a great mental model for it.
Think about a last topic for today. I
want to close uh close on the say sort
of the bridge between legacy and new
media because we see just give some
examples. Obviously, the New York Times
they've made the adjustment to the new
world um very well from a business
perspective. You know, we had um CBS
acquire the Free Press, and so there's
some, you know, acquisitions there uh
strategic acquisitions for legacy media
companies who are trying to innovate.
You know, uh on MTS ourselves, we're
sort of experimenting with with players
from both worlds. You know, we have um
new school of podcasters and Twitch
streamer, you know, Theo is Theo is 21
years old?
Yeah. 20 Yeah, he's born to be a a
Twitch streamer, but we also have I
mean, 21, I mean, over the hill. Yeah,
exactly. What, you know?
>> [laughter]
>> Has been by now. Gray hair, gray hair.
Washed. Yeah, washed.
But, we also have Mark Halperin who uh
you know, as a you know, legacy and
legendary um you know, uh commentator
and host who who funny enough uh Uh,
know, we've talked about how
is the is the bridge figure uh in that
he was successful both in legacy and in
this new media media climate. Um, and
it's rare for people to do both.
Halperin, of course, interviewed did a
very famous interview with Trump when he
was talking about the Bible verses and
getting getting him uh
to mention some specific ones and you
know, Trump of course didn't want to
pick favorites. Um,
anyway, I'm I'm curious how you think
about the sort of the bridge um
either analysis of
Trump as a bridge or or more just how do
you see legacy players and new media
players um sort of you know, playing out
or even the styles of what will work in
this new new format.
Yeah, I mean, so I guess
I don't know, you maybe start with data,
right? So, um the data shows that
basically
Um, so if you focus on American data cuz
what I'm most familiar with. So, just in
the data you basically see a couple
things. So, one is um trust in
centralized institutions of all kinds is
is collapsing in the US. Um, so
basically any kind of legacy
um or um
incumbent institution you know, trust is
collapsing fast. By the way, that
collapse in trust didn't start with the
internet. It actually started around
1970. Um,
it actually
uh it actually it's it's part of this
it's part of this WTF happened in 1971
uh meme um is when basically trust in
centralized institutions in the US
started to fall off a cliff.
Um, that's true for many kinds of
centralized institutions and it's been
true for you know, basically 55 years.
Um, but but media's included in that.
Um, and so trust in centralized media is
collapsing and you know, keeps hitting
new record lows basically every time
they run the survey it collapses
further.
Um, and so so that's certainly true. And
then you and then the the business
version of it is just very clear which
is you know, we've talked about CNN
later like you're earlier like you know,
ratings for all the centralized media
properties are in full scale collapse.
Um, you know, cable news is collapsing.
Um, you know, almost every almost every
newspaper has collapsed. Um, almost
every magazine has collapsed. Um,
you know, basically all the all the all
the legacy formats have collapsed. Um
Uh you know, with only very very rare
exceptions. Um and so, you know, just
and then by the way, of course, finally,
it's just sort of obvious, you know, the
the rise of podcasts obviously is is
obvious now. Um
and by the way, it's amazing like the
election of '24 was the one where
podcasts kind of flipped the you know,
it went from being like, I don't know if
this matters to like all of a sudden
everybody's like, oh wow, this matters
like a lot. Um and so, the rise of
podcasts of course is undeniable at this
point. The rise of social media, the
rise of of live streaming. Um you know,
these things are clearly happening. And
so, like the the the the changing of the
guard, reordering of the the businesses
and of the cultural and social phenomena
are clearly happening and I think are
undeniable. Um you know, if you
extrapolate forward, like obviously all
you know, essentially all of the
remaining old media properties that
don't figure out a way to adapt uh to
the new world are going to you know,
they're they're you know, going to get
basically run
as my private equity and that'll be
that. Um you know, which is kind of the
story of the newspaper industry industry
these days. Um
so so I you know, that that like it's
almost like not even interesting to say
that anymore just cuz it's like it's so
obvious that that's happening and then,
you know, obviously social media, you
know, continues to grow as a phenomenon.
Um
uh continues to be very important. Um
uh and so, yeah. And you know, look,
we're still we're still living in this
we're we're still living in a in a
hybrid world today, right? Um and so,
we're still living in a world um in
which like, you know, to some extent it
still matters what's on TV, but like not
nearly as much as it did, but you know,
pretty soon it's not it's not going to
anymore. So, uh you know, so so so that
world is changing fast. Um yeah, I I
just think yeah, the
the main thing is going to be um you
know, the the the the people who adapt
to that are are people who adapt to that
are going to adapt to that. Um and
they're they're either going to adapt or
they're not. Um you know, you mentioned
Mark Mark Halperin, you know, who's a
good good friend of both of ours. Um and
you know, he's I think he's doing like
an amazing job adapting to that and in a
way that's just like I would say
shockingly different um and better than
you know, most of his former former
colleagues.
Um you know, there's great examples that
you know, then you get The New York
Times has adapted to that in an
interesting way.
Um you know, the the Hasan um um a
a newspaper um has fully committed
itself to um
to the future, let's say.
Um so, you know, they're they're doing
their thing.
Um yeah,
you know, most of legacy properties
won't adapt. They, you know, they never
do. Um there's going to be lots and lots
of new things um that emerge. Um
And maybe I I should say here again to
not sound not sound cynical about this,
like
it is really striking.
I'll say the following. So, like what
are the two like mega mega mega trends
in video uh and and and and by the way,
also in politics over the course of last
like 5 years. It's basically two things.
It's it's short-form video in the form
of TikTok, Instagram, and and and and X,
you know, short-form, you know, Reels uh
or short-form video. Uh and and there
you get like the full battery of
accusations of like, you know,
destroying attention span and
everything's trivial.
Um but on the other side is the rise of
the 3-hour podcast.
Um and so on the on the podcast side,
you have this incredible phenomenon with
3 hours. And by the way, some of these,
you know, Joe and and Lex and others are
now pushing this to the point where, you
know, Lex now has like in some cases
7-hour podcasts, right? I think what is
it biology did like a 10-hour one on
10-hour one on Lex. Yeah, yeah. So,
biology went for 10 hours on Lex. Um and
so and it's actually interesting cuz if
you talk to those guys, they get data on
completion rates. Um and and it's
actually a very large percentage of
their of their listeners or viewers who
actually listen to the whole thing.
Um so, like many many many Rogan
podcasts or Lex podcasts, people
actually listen to the full the full 3
hours.
Um and so so it's it's the thing I
really rejected this idea that like, you
know, I don't want people to think that
I believe this is like this idea that
everything is going to become just like
trivial short-form social media
like that. No, not at all. You have this
correspond
You do have a lot of that. But you have
this corresponding thing, which is you
also it's like a it's like a barbell.
You also have this You you have this
massive rise in substance.
Um and on the substance side, I would
point to the long-form podcasts. I would
point to Substack. Um by the way, you
know, there's a big push on X to have
long-form essays. Um I would push uh you
know, online you know, online online you
know, courses uh on every topic are
available. Um and um uh you just yeah,
you have this ability. But I've even AI
what my favorite feature of AI is what
they call deep research. Uh which is a
feature on both I think it's on
particularly on ChatGPT and on Claude,
but like you set it loose and it will
write you like literally 30 pages. Uh a
30-page answer, you know, this is
basically like a textbook on any topic.
Um and so so I I think there there is
this other side which is you you have
this you also have this growth in you
have this growth in Oh, the other thing
is just in we're an example of this, the
rise of the practitioner media.
Uh
practitioner-driven media. So,
people who are actually doing a thing
showing up and talking about it.
Um and of course, you know, that leads
to all sorts of outrage of that's not
journalism if you don't have somebody
asking like whatever super you know,
snippy critical questions about it or
whatever. But like the idea for somebody
who is actually doing a thing, I mean,
you know, Andre Karpathy in AI, right?
He just
just like shows up and like explains
like here here is how this all works.
Um is is is just like amazing. And and
you know, in in in old media like
basically like when I when I was younger
like Charlie Rose did that.
But so I grew up actually listening to
Charlie Rose watching Charlie Rose. But
Charlie Rose literally was on at
midnight. Like he was on CBS at midnight
and he would have these hour-long
conversations with these super
interesting people doing super
interesting things, but he was on at
midnight and you had to stay up at
midnight to watch Charlie Rose. Right?
It was like it was one of the great
things about getting a DVR is you could
record, you know, Charlie Rose and watch
it during during normal normal daylight
hours. But you know, we lost that or we
didn't have that for a very long time
and we have that now. And so so I do
think it's worth noting like there is
this incredible in my view clearly
incredibly positive, informative,
educational, super helpful, super
constructive thing on the other side
which is of course a lot of what we try
to do.
And
you know, if 2024 was the podcast
election,
it'll be interesting to see what 2028
people have been very concerned, you
know, or or sort of predicting, you
know, deep fakes for a while and how
that might influence things, but we
haven't really seen
anything there super material it it
seems, but it'll be interesting to see
what what media formats or just how the
2028 election is is different than the
2024 one in
this conversation.
We've had deepfakes forever.
>> [laughter]
>> Like
Like people have believed all kinds of
crazy
Um I mean, you know, there was there was
the Gulf of Tonkin incident and they
kicked off the really kicked off the
Vietnam War. Like I think we now know
that that was a fish. Like it's actually
quite well established. Um then some
people might say Russiagate.
Um
it was it turned turns out it was quite
an elaborate fake.
Um so I the the deepfake thing I find
very funny cuz it's like it's not like
we've been swimming in truth all this
time and all of a sudden now that now
there's going to be deepfakes. But
anyway, that maybe that's a a separate
conversation. The um
I think the the the
the the substantive comment I would make
is um
So uh
So I actually think we have People talk
about like famously talk about the 1960
election Kennedy versus Nixon where
where famously where television took
over from radio. Uh where if if you they
had their famous debate and if you
listened to the radio you thought Nixon
won and if you watched it on TV you
thought that the the the Kennedy won. Uh
so so so you know, the the the the you
know, audio versus audio plus video. Um
and so people have been talking for a
while you know, that was considered like
the first television election where
television was like the determining
factor in who won or lost.
Um along with you know, maybe some
shenanigans in Chicago.
>> [laughter]
>> Anyway,
um
Speaking of deepfakes.
Um
so uh anyway, um people have been
talking for a while about um when will
there be the first internet election? Um
and and you know, people like to point
to 2016 being you know, Trump using
social media or maybe 2024 being the
podcast election. I actually think the
first internet election hasn't happened
yet. I I I
By the way, people even point to 2008
with which with Obama fundraising. So
yeah, 2008 Obama fundraising online. Uh
2016 Trump using using social media as a
broadcast method and then 2024 podcast.
So we've had three examples of internet
mattering for elections for sure.
Uh but I think we haven't had the true
internet election and and I and and and
as a consequence of that and and by the
way we therefore haven't really had the
true internet candidate yet. And
actually it's interesting as people talk
this is not a pro or negative pro or con
comment on on Trump himself for the
purpose of this discussion, but people
talk about Trump as the internet
candidate, but he really he's really a
hybrid. Um, in that he cares he cares
enormously about what's on TV. Um, and
he's on and he's and he's on TV a lot
um, and he watches TV all the time
famously in order to cuz TV is basically
how he gets a read on the pulse of of
sort of what's happening and of what
people think about things and what
people So like I think I think Trump's
kind of underlying theory is the things
that are on TV are the things that the
people running the TV network know that
their viewers want to see. And so
therefore if you watch this on TV you
can get a sense of what people actually
think and I you know and as TV has been
the dominant medium for the last 60 or
70 years, you know, that I you know,
it's a pretty good theory. Obviously
it's it's it's pretty well you know,
quite well for him.
Um, and then he and then he he also like
cares a lot about like affecting what's
on TV.
Um, and and there's this there's this
famous Trump story that lots of people
have told where he'll be in a meeting
and there'll be a TV on in the
background he'll be watching it and
he'll he'll have it with the sound off,
but he'll be watching the Chiron the you
know, the thing at the bottom of the
screen the text that shows what what
they're what they're saying and if he
doesn't like what's on the Chiron he'll
tweet something to change the subject.
Right. And so he'll tweet and then he'll
literally watch and the Chiron will
change and he'll be like ah, you know,
so he right he's right he's able to
cause right he's able to single-handedly
with his power of his Twitter to turn
one current thing into another current
thing, right? Okay.
So so my my point is like he's he's a
hybrid. He So he's he's very social
media fluent, but he's also very
television. And of course his entire
career was made on television. So he's
he's very television fluent. He's one of
the best you know, television
programmers in history. And he's and
he's and he's a social media native. Um,
there will be an internet candidate.
There will be an internet president who
gets elected and I I believe entirely
based on the internet.
Um, where they don't pay any attention
at all to what's on TV.
Um, because it doesn't matter to them
one bit. Um, and they're going to be
entirely online and they're not going to
care what's in the on TV and they're not
going to care what's in the newspaper
and they're going to be 100% a creature
of the internet. Um, and and I think we
haven't I I believe we haven't seen that
yet. I don't know when we're going to
see it. I'm pretty sure
possible it's 20 Um, probably my guess
is 32.
Um, yeah. And so I I think we all have
Yes.
For better or for worse, we all have we
all have that to look forward to. Yeah.
The uh well, I think that's a great note
to to wrap on. This has been a great
discussion all things media. Uh Mark,
thank you for coming on the first day of
Monitoring the Situation.
I am proud to be part of the monitoring.
Excellent.